e
for e
good evening everyone we're going to get
started in just a few minutes there are
some additional chairs along the back
row which you are welcome to set up but
I would just ask that you keep a center
aisle clear um and uh enough room on
either side that there is safety grass
in the room thank you
and also with that being said there are
some additional seats I'm seeing up here
and if you have an empty seat next to
you
wave your hands so everyone has a place
to sit if they
wish e
good evening everyone it is a bit after
6:30 so we are going to get started
again there should be some extra chairs
stacked along the back if you wish to
have a seat during the meeting um we
just ask that you keep aisles clear for
safe safe eress in the room um Now call
to order this meeting of Lancaster City
Council for March 11th 2025 a few
reminders at the top of the meeting for
everyone please take a moment to silence
your phones and devices if you haven't
done so already this meeting and its
participants are being recorded and live
streamed anyone addressing councel
during public comment periods should
please do so at the podium in order to
be heard in the room and on the live
stream please begin all comments with
your name and block of residence for our
meeting record public comment is limited
to 3 minutes per speaker I will be using
this light in front of me to keep time
it will turn green when 3 minutes begins
it will turn yellow when there is one
minute remaining and it will turn red
when 3 minutes has been exhausted and I
want to thank everyone in advance for
ensuring that everyone has an equal time
um also just a meeting uh a meeting note
the women's History Month resolution
that was slated for this evening has
been postponed until our next regular
meeting and now for all of those who are
willing and able please rise for the
Pledge of
Allegiance I pledge allegiance to the
flag
of the United States of America and to
the repic for it stands one nation under
God
indivisible and justice for
all Mr Harris would you please call the
rooll of members yes Madam
president Mr Med here Mr royya here Mr
kis here M Craig Miss Diaz here Mr hsh
here and president B here councilor
Craig is excused this
evening we will now move to the approval
of the minutes of the February 25th 2025
meeting motion to approve second second
we have a motion and a second any
Council comments on the meeting
minutes hearing none Mr Harris Mr Matt I
Mr Royo I Mr GLE i m Diaz hi Mr h i and
president b
i next item is proclamations honors and
awards and resolutions of recognition
again as I noted at the top of the
meeting the women's History Month
resolution is postponed until our next
regular meeting that will take us to our
first public comment period reserve for
residents who contacted the city clerk
prior to the meeting to request to speak
in this period again comments are
limited to three minutes per speaker and
must begin with your name and block of
residents before go into public comment
we have several and I know that the
there is a topic that I believe everyone
is uh here for I want to just make a
quick statement I would like to ensure
members of the public that the use of uh
use of force review for the March 2nd
incident is underway currently the
review will involve a thorough
examination of all body cameras and
other footage that is available members
of council and the public will be
updated on the findings when the review
is completed while I understand that the
video posted online is a small part of
an interaction I agree personally that
what I saw was disturbing and I look
forward to hearing the outcome of the
review and from Chief Mendes during a
more formal report to council from a
public safety that has been requested by
councelor Amed that will occur at an
upcoming
meeting Mr Harris if we could begin with
public comment please yes Madam
president uh first this evening is AIA
moios is Alia
here next is Grace
muser his grace muser in the
room we can recall these names at the
end next Mr Harris Andrea
hirch I'm sorry Adriana
H good
evening good
evening uh good evening Council in my
capacity as the former executive
director of the common wheel I got to
know the youth on bikes who we
affectionately refer to as the wheelie
kids and like many teens their age it
took a lot of time and effort to get to
know them and more importantly earn
their trust
teens are by no means perfect I should
know I was once a teen uh we know their
frontal loes are not developed until 25
years of age and that they will make
mistakes sometimes the same ones time
after time however this does not warrant
police to use Force against them when I
worked with the wheelie kids I would
encourage safe behavior when I witnessed
law breaking I instructed my staff to
withhold the services they sought out
weekly because actions do have
consequences perhaps our police could
call parents and impound bicycles
without resorting to force still
imparting lessons while doing less harm
further still I'd encourage police to
use part of their Community engagement
budget which they did not fully spend in
2024 to buy bike lights to give to kids
I think working to build trust with them
through positive engagement would go a
long way for them to follow the law I
would also encourage our police get out
of their vehicles which by Nature
insulate all of us from the world around
us police used to be beat cops getting
to know neighborhoods and neighbors now
they drive through our city waiting to
be called to a crime we need to know and
trust our police not to have them behind
the closed doors of a police
SUV many people think wheelie kids are a
menace but their bikes give them purpose
they practice tricks day and night
meanwhile I can barely let go of one
handlebar to
signal and I've been told bikes keep
them out of gangs perhaps with more
emotional intelligence training our
police can approach our teens from a
place of understanding and compassion
thank
you Mr Harris our next speaker yes Mr
President next is Nick s Hiller
[Music]
good evening evening uh Nick Hiller 400
block or 500 block of North Plum Street
um I'm not going to hide my frustration
and anger right now because I've been
living in this city for 10 years and
over those 10 years I've seen the police
repeatedly brutalize black and brown
youth in this
city when I first moved here a couple
years after I first moved here we all
saw the video of a man sitting on with
his hands behind his back on the
sidewalk get tased in the back while
following orders that was my one of my
earliest introductions to
Lancaster and repeatedly in 2020 I know
I've talked to you all a lot in here on
during 2020 I saw police officers
brutalize youth in the streets
protesting for their rights including
pepper spraying folks in Point Blank
Range and I got some of that pepper
spray because of the wind myself so I've
seen seen repeatedly repeatedly this
brutality that our police officers du to
our communities and it frustrates
me because we see how open the city is
to Rich tourists and not our own
neighbors I am one of the I'm a member
and organizer with the party for
socialism and Liberation and I'm one of
the co-signers of I'm sure the statement
that you've all seen and I just would
like to reiterate those statements and I
hope other signers will reiterate them
and other will repeat them one the
demand is to reinstate the civilian
review board formerly known as a
community police working group that uh
that was dismantled with no reason uh no
reason announced the public two we call
for the firing of Officer Hatfield and
the names of the unidentified officers
from Chief Mendes's Police Department
present at the scene to be released and
three for the police to uphold
accountability and transparency with the
community by releasing the body cam uh
body camera footage to the public many
of you
have bought out statements calling for
accountability and transparency in vague
terms these are just three of the first
steps that you can take to actually
demonstrate that transparency and
accountability that you're boasting that
you support thank
you Mr Harris yes next is Jessica Lopez
good evening good evening my name is
Jessica Lopez I'm a Lancaster City
resident I refuse to give my address out
of safety concerns I'm sure you guys
understand um I'm going to start with
the nice part I
appreciate counselor Ed I appreciate
counselor Oro I appreciate and you Mr
kle say I appreciate you miss
Bay and I do appreciate you Mr H I'm
going to start with the nice part your
guys' statements were on the money I
appreciate you using your voice and
advocating in that faction do I believe
that city council
could possibly do a little bit more to
push the education of these kids for
these kids
every year yes they could because every
year we have new kids that get to ride
bikes because they get old enough to
ride bikes every year those kids grow
they don't get handed the bicycle crime
code those kids
get they get helmets they get knee pads
they get sat on their bikes they learn
how to ride those bikes and nobody tells
them what the laws are me as a mother
before this situation transpired tied I
didn't know what the bike laws
were how do you expect every mother in
this city to work hard to pay taxes and
then know all your bike crime
codes now with that being said it takes
a village to raise a
child and our elected officials to hold
those put in place to protect them
accountable Chief Mendes's police
department and his absent present in the
community he grew up in and his failure
to control his officers has shown the
black and brown community that they
afford US no protections and that we
should fear interactions with them I do
not let my children go
outside what should have been a teaching
moment by officers to these kids turned
into a traumatic life-altering event
those kids will never look at their
bikes or any cop in the same way ever
again that's
right the statement that the police
department released
today is not only slandering these
children because prove it yes
prove that each and every one of those
kids that were assaulted committed those
acts that still
don't deserve that response none of
those things on that list says put your
hands on
me if those children are not in
immediate danger to our community are to
ourselves and that doesn't mean bumping
into somebody with their bike
there's no reason why those grown men
with guns put their hands on
them so the police department's response
M lope I'm we've gone quite over my
three minutes give me just give me just
just cuz I got to get this out the
police department's response to what to
to what to defend an officer who stood
by while his fellow officer punch a man
in the face in
2015 he didn't protect that
man to what protect the man who was
listed with Ryan Yoder in a civil rights
claim in 2023 to protect him who was
listed two months ago in another civil
rights
lawsuit this is all public information
online because what you are protecting
them more than you're protecting us at
what point do you cage your daughter
the city of Lancaster is known for its
gross misconduct issues and use
continually past the buck instead of
taking responsibility and action and
Janet Diaz's statement is a prime
example of the outof touch advocacy and
gaslighting that transpires in this
community I pray you never become our
mayor the the mayors the exiting mayor's
silence on this situation proves she
never belonged
here we are no longer accepting the
status quo and the complacency that
transpires among those who we put on a
pedestal is long gone we're tired of
being used and accepting abuse
disregarded and manipulated we are not
here for youed to look
good we are not here for use
we put yall in place for us to protect
our kids and our community and with that
I will walk away and I like I said I
thank those who chose to use their
platform to advocate for these kids but
at this point more needs to be
done I shouldn't be getting these videos
on Sunday night and spending N9 days
[ __ ] organizing this this is wrong I
do not get paid by the city and I'm
tired of being
[Music]
thank you
Miss Mr Harris our next speaker next
speaker is darling
bird Miss Bird good even hi darling bird
um first I want to talk about two other
issues before we address the police
issue uh two Council meetings ago I was
here and I requested a report about how
many people got tickets on the day that
it snowed when our trash set out 3 weeks
I have not heard from any council person
about that report or the number I know
it's very high it's in the Southeast
area I'm here again to request that
report I have an email for you I just
got this afternoon oh okay thank you
also I'm here to I addressed the issue
about the uh a report on how many
accidents was on um East 10 Avenue on
Franklin Street that they got a stuff
sign put there when we have been
requesting since 20177 that a stop sign
be placed on green and an Street which
is a very dangerous intersection we have
many members from the community come to
this meeting and many traffic meetings
and we're not heard and we're no longer
going to say we're not going to be heard
we want are we're talking about safety
now with the police we requested a
Citizens review board so many years ago
it is time that we get a Citizens review
board to bring trust and communication
into the community thank
you Mr Harris our next speaker next
speaker is the black voter Outreach
network of
Pennsylvania I understand that the
representative for this organization
could not be here this evening so I have
allowed a second speaker I will
reiterate that we need to keep time for
everyone thank you yes I'm going to come
up and hand you guys's proposed
resolution and along with that I'm also
going to hand you the city of
Lancaster's commitment to racial Equity
that came out in 2020 that has not been
put in place and we feel is not being
followed
thank you so
much good evening my name is Jessica
Lopez and I'm here today speaking on
half of John
Maya he and I are proudly representing
the colle Ive a coalition following
Lancaster organizations the black voter
Outreach network of PA the Democratic
Socialist of America the Lancaster Bale
fund the Lancaster the Lancaster change
makers Collective Lancaster stands up
and the party for socialism and
Liberation tonight we are submitting a
document for public record that outlines
concerns regarding the Lancaster City
Police Department's recent interactions
with black and Latino residents
specifically this document highlights
the March 2nd 2025 incident involving
the use of force against several Latino
teens as well as other recent cases that
have raised serious concerns about
transparency and accountability within
the department we recognize that Chief
Mendes is a lifelong Lancaster resident
and a veteran officer in this city given
his deep ties to the community we
believe it is reasonable to expect
leadership that actively Works to
improve trust between law enforcement
and the public particularly for
marginalized communities however the
continued use of force and lack of
deescalation involving black and Latino
residences raised significant questions
what steps are being taken to prevent
incidences like this from happening
again how does the police department
ensure officers follow the escalation
policies before res resorting to
force why are previous uses of force
reports unavailable to the
public repeat why are previous use of
force reports unavailable to the public
public and when will they be made
[Music]
accessible and I guess this would go for
Janet but what does your Public Safety
Committee do do they work with the
police directly or are we letting them
lead
this our request tonight is
straightforward we urge the city council
to consider passing a reasonable
resolution calling for an immediate
transparent and independent review of
this latest incident and public
available findings additionally we asked
to create a formal Public Safety commiss
or authority that includes Council and
community members and provides oversight
on policing policies along with the
commission we ask for a Community
Partnership including a civilian review
board these are measures necessary first
steps to establish trust between law
enforcements and the communities where
they serve our Collective formally
acknowledges the Lancaster City Police
Department statement on the incident on
31025 they released a vague statement
that left that left us with more
concerns than answers this response is
unacceptable and not enough an unsigned
statement informing the public of
internal investigation is not reasonable
transparent or acceptable for behavior
that is a pattern the decisions made in
response to this issue will send a clear
message about Lancaster City's
commitment to Public Safety
accountability and Justice there are
opportunities here to take the first
step in building trust with the
community we look forward to working
collaboratively to ensure all residents
feel protected respected and Hur please
accept this resolution on request on our
behalf we look forward to your responses
thank you very
much and that was John Maya not
just
peace Mr Harris our next speaker next
speaker is D the
gas good evening evening uh my name is
darl Legacy I live in the 100 block of
north
Mary uh thank you for allowing me to
address the council I'm here to talk
about the interaction that happened that
we're probably all here for um people
say that you don't know what happened
before the video started they say the
kids were doing wheelies they were going
the wrong way down the street maybe yeah
maybe they were that doesn't justify
having someone two to three times the
weight of that kid with his knee on his
back face down not resisting crying for
help like that just when you look at
that I don't know how you can see that
and say oh yeah that's the right
response I hear a lot of people complain
about cancel culture they say they're
afraid to be canceled for saying the
wrong thing or doing the wrong thing
what I don't see our police worried
about being canceled I don't see police
officers worried about what it looks
like when they kneel on someone saying
they can't breathe we've done this for
five years really for a hundred years
and I don't see them being worried when
they push someone who's recording them
which happened twice in that video it's
unacceptable so I'm calling for four
things one release the names of all the
police officers involved in that
situation release all the body cam
footage leading up to and during the
encounter rein at the community police
working group and require deescalation
training for all officers to everyone
here and everyone in the city I'm asking
you to record every single public police
encounter from now
on and especially those with people of
color I realize I'm a white person I am
privileged I mostly don't have to worry
about this I don't want to be here
speaking tonight but I feel like I have
to be it's your constitutional right to
record police if it is in public amen
so I hear people say oh you complain
about the police and then you're the
first one to go running to them when you
need something yeah that's the job okay
that's their job no one made them become
police officers no one said they had to
do this if this is too hard or if
they're not happy they can quit they
work for us not the other way around
our next speaker next speaker is Megan
Keller it's Megan here with us
toight I'll recall the names from the
beginning and hers at the end our next
speaker Mr Harris speaker is John Till
Tolen good evening good evening um John
Tolen the first and only block of
yav I recently saw a video that
Disturbed me uh a toddler held at
gunpoint by police was lying on the
ground beside her mother both bellied
down forced into submission so imagine
being a child barely old enough to form
full sentences having to stay perfectly
still so you aren't killed by a trigger
happy
officer the footage from March 2nd is
equally disturbing what we saw was not
just an overreach it was intimidation
abuse of power and a blatant disregard
for the rights of our youth miners
stopped for lacking bike reflectors at
6:30 p.m. it's hardly a justification
for
detention and yet they were treated like
criminals the law is clear minors cannot
be questioned without a parent present
but instead of
protection these children were met with
Force w't even pin down to the ground
and an offer some nailing on his back
imagine being that teenager doing your
best to remain calm while being
terrified and why shouldn't they be
afraid in a country where a 12-year-old
boy was gunned down for playing a toy
gun fear is rational they God some these
kids knew their rights thank God one of
them filled the interaction because
without that recording we might not be
having this
conversation I know fear personally and
as a child too I was abused by police I
too have felt the weight of an officer's
force and I know that trauma doesn't end
when the moment is over it lingers
leaving scars that can take years and
even a lifetime to heal seeing the
events on March 2nd chills me to my bone
because I know what happens when power
goes unchecked who is the enemy here the
children riding their bikes or a system
that continues to terrorize the most
vulnerable Among
Us lanter is a city of contrast and
there is so much Beauty here yet we
continue to make headlines for excessive
force and police misconduct our history
hasn't been kind to people of color to
the poor to the UN house or anyone
deemed marginalizing in these moments
history repeats itself there is a clear
disconnect between some officers in the
communities they are meant to serve we
cannot afford to have police offices
patrolling neighborhoods they do not
understand or respect community policing
true community policing is about
relationships trust guidance and not
intimidation a missing bike reflector
should be should be a teachable moment
not an excuse for aggression I
understand that officers are human but a
a bad day for them should not become a
lifelong trauma for someone
else the people of Lancaster
most importantly our children deserve
better they deserve to play to exercise
to Simply exist without the looming
threat of police brutality if we claim
to be a just City we must act like one
and that starts with accountability that
starts with asking why this officer is
still in the force and what we should do
to rectify this
situation so I also Echo the Coalition
of local orgs who have issued the
statement with the demands of
reinstating the civilian review board
firing officer Hatfield releasing body
footage and I ask you to think about
Community think about your own children
and think about creating better dialogue
with our community about how we treat
one another thank
you Mr Harris our next speaker please
forever
our next speaker is Amber
farward good evening hi my name is Amber
farward from the 700 block of Fifth
Street I am uh a citizen of this city
I've been my entire adult life and uh I
am currently missing my son's first
soccer practice to be here to do all
this with you guys because I am a mother
um this is very important to me I want
my son you know I see my son in that
child in that video and I want a safe
place for him to run around with his
friends and have fun and ride his bike
without fear um I don't feel that right
now in this city um and my other point
that I wanted to make is that I'm a
licensed professional counselor I've DED
dedicated my career to working with
children and advocating for them and
keeping them safe if I ever was told or
saw a video of one of my clients being
kneeled on by an adult I would have to
contact child protective
services
and and I couldn't in good conscience
not show up here today and ask that you
all keep our children safe m
where is our next speaker next speaker
is David Miller
Glick good evening good evening
my name is David Miller Glick and I live
in on haaker Street in Lancaster City
I'm a volunteer organizer with Lancaster
stands up and I stand before you today
as a concerned Citizen and a father who
is both fearful and angry I'm angry
because officer Hatfield and all other
officers who were present during the
march 2 incident failed to act like
adults much less officers of the law
there is no excuse for a routine traffic
stop to escalate to the point where
grown men are forcing a 15 and
16-year-old to the ground with knees on
their
backs it is proof of a deep moral
failure on the part of the police
officers involved as well as systemic
issues that will only get worse if
ignored I am disappointed by the police
department statement which listed minor
infractions such as trespassing in
garage
and pulling fire alarms which was a lazy
attempt to paint these boys as dangerous
criminals I would like to ask everyone
in this room who seems more dangerous a
few Rowdy teenagers or the grown adults
who violently pinned them to the
pavement and made them fear for their
lives what we need is accountability not
excuses my son is 9 years old his skin
is brown he loves to ride his bike with
me I'm here today because I hope he will
never be a victim of the brutality like
we saw on the March 2 incident he
deserves to be able to ride his bike
through the city without fear of
arbitrary violence from police officers
who have no business wearing the
badge I demand accountability
I agree with all of the statement all of
the asks from the statement of
reestablishing the citizen review board
and releasing the body cam footage but
especially officer fat Hatfield needs to
be
[Music]
fired we need to show that his b that
his behavior was unacceptable even one
bad Apple can spoil the bunch thank
you next speaker is Susie
Gomez good evening good evening Susie
Gomez 100 block of North Reservoir
Street pushing an ungodly agenda while
swearing an oath to protect the people
is being rebuked today you look down on
us by your ignorance and can't believe
that the S&P 500 is based on the
standard and poor you see things through
the eyes of the wicked who pursued their
agenda to kill steal and destroy there
is no unity in this administration
because us as taxpayers who have
expressed ourselves on this Podium gets
ignored delayed or denied let's talk you
say set up an appointment you say but
public comments are suggestions concerns
Etc we work
too and pay you to do your
job Lancaster City has lost its Customs
Heritage Foundation its name
Lancaster and so Lancaster has become
the home of survival to divide and
conquer has always been the quest and
you pray on the innocent hard workers
because you are too busy closing down
departments relying on it social
technology with troubleshooting
interruptions the government creates
funding for all cities and states and
the workers write the grants push the
intake coordinators to execute the
applications to fulfill the needs of the
people while while they pay their taxes
to be the Commonwealth that we both
invest in this is not a one-way
Street your ignorance has taught a
generation to measure their work on
takeaways as City contracts are being
run by Outsiders permits are forced to
use Benchmark investors are catching tax
breaks and shareholders seem to be the
only ones receiving Equitable gain
for centuries this city relied on
volunteers interns graduates and
neighborhoods to find an even balance
and take care of our public officers
while taking pride in the building of
infrastructures cleaning of parks
working together as one so that the
Baton can be passed to the next graduate
who takes pride in the city engagements
but this
Administration has us continuously
asking for loans passing on properties
to the highest bidder while handing
investors L A baitman condemn properties
that can be REM that can be
remedied that can be remedied by
Community programs such as critical
repair Government funding grants to help
in crisis for homelessness lack of
Housing
revitalization and more looking at you
instead it's better to pour
80% for a new turf at a baseball field
than helping a taxpayer or nonprofit
struggling to maintain their business
churches are a nonprofit but you rather
open up new
nonprofits shame on you we last thing
I'm sorry we are supposed to be a common
wealth common interest you will go down
as the worst Administration in Lancaster
PA who killed the American dream and
broke all the
rules
don't Mr Harris our next speaker for
this comment period next speaker is
Monda
REITs
Manda right we'll recall names at the
end uh next speaker then Mr Harris
Marshall
Miller good evening good evening
Marshall Miller uh 100th block of East
Vine Street thank you all for your time
um I'm here to stand with my neighbors
and say that the recent violent
incidents involving Lancaster City
police and local teenagers were deeply
disturbing and
unacceptable this and other recent
videos of violent police interactions
were alarm to me and I believe they
undermine the Community Trust in
Lancaster City's police our police work
for us as City residents we pay their
salaries and we have the right to demand
the highest quality of service from
them I recognize that our police
officers have a difficult and important
job to do and I'm thankful for the
countless times they do that well but
part of their work involves
accountability when we witness what
appears to be a clear failure to protect
our kids these violent incidents have
broken trust in city leaders owe
residents a thorough transparent
investigation into each one I believe uh
these recent incidents require more than
a regular review they require robust
more transparent investigations than
your typical use of force
reviews our Police Department owes this
to Residents in order to reestablish
trust and I hope that you all will help
us get that done moving forward what I
would like to see from this chamber and
city leaders is a renewed effort to
recruit officers from within the city
when someone lives on your block they
are far less likely to put their knee on
your kid's back for riding a bike on the
sidewalk when our officers live among us
they can know residents personally give
them a call when they see their kids in
trouble or getting into trouble that is
the power of community policing and we
have to build that and I'd like to make
a practical suggestion on that front
currently in the city's officer
recruitment process preference points
are added to applicants test scores to
help boost certain applicants based on
their background and experience for
example veterans are given 10 preference
points on top of their cumulative test
scores according to state law no other
preference points can exceed this amount
but it is my understanding that we can
tweak other preference points below this
amount based on other criteria currently
in our police officer application
process three preference points are
given to candidates who live within the
city's limits uh for 2 years prior to
their test date also three preference
points are given to candidates who can
communicate in a second language I would
like you all to help increase these
amounts to help increase the number of
successful candidates who live in the
city I think a good place to start would
be at least uh to double the current
preference points for City residents so
that would be six preference points for
candidates who lived within the city for
at least two years and I suggest we also
increase the preference points for
candidates who can communicate in a
second language this should help build a
police force that looks and lives looks
like us and lives in the communities
that they serve which ultimately makes
them more accountable to us the
residents who pay their salaries thank
you for your time and service um I look
forward to seeing how you take real
action to change the status
quo our next speaker next speaker is an
Tores
good evening hi my name is an Torres I
live in litz I'm here this evening with
a statement on behalf of the Langster
Democratic Socialist of America the
incident that occurred on March 2nd in
Lancaster City between the Lancaster
City police and the miners riding their
bikes was reprehensible we as an
organization with members who live and
work in the city demand action and
accountability police officers cannot be
allowed to act with impunity they cannot
be allowed to forego City policy and use
Force before a deescalation and there is
no reason why in interaction with
children riding their bik should end
with high level force and arrest is it
policy for the Lancaster Police to
violently arrest children who don't have
reflectors on their bikes we hear the
concerns of the people that say well
what happened before the camera started
rolling and to that we ask in return
When is it okay for children to be the
victim of excessive use of force where
is the line
drawn we see time and time again Ines of
police violence including in our own
City when will it end what is the final
STW before people stand up and say
enough and demand more from those sworn
to protect us if we allow officers
involved in this police department and
at large to be free from punishment what
is next and if this is what we see when
they are being recorded what is
happening when no one is
looking statements about this incident
from members on this Council and to the
police department talk of transparency
and accountability a good first start of
this would be the following
one a reinstatement of the civilian
review board formerly known as the
community police working group two the
termination of Officer Hatfield and the
names of the unidentified police
officers from the scene who work for
chief menace's police department to be
released three for the city to uphold
accountability and transparency with the
community by releasing the body Cam Body
cam footage to the
public additionally lanaster DSA demands
that any review of the conduct that
happened on March 2nd to be evaluate by
an independent third party reviewer the
police cannot be trusted to evaluate and
investigate
themselves an independent thirdparty
investigation will allow for an unbi
review free from conflict of interest
the police officers in this city will
continue to feel emboldened and increase
their use of force with impunity if
there are no consequences for their
actions if this is allowed to happen we
will remember this moment and who
ignored their community's call to action
so please do do not let us down help us
take action
[Music]
now Mr Harris our next speaker next
speaker is Michelle
B good
evening my name is Michelle bat I am the
President of the Lancaster bail fund but
I am not here today my capacity as that
uh president Jessica Lopez spoke well
enough for our organization and for
herself I am here as an
attorney I am
a specifically I had the uh privilege of
serving our indigent crimin criminal uh
defendant population for a number of
years I have practiced criminal defense
for close to a decade now and I am
deeply disturbed by what I have been
seeing recently not just the March
2nd uh incident but pepper spraying of
children taking a black woman to the
ground
over
nothing in my practice I
have gotten good results for my clients
due to police
brutality in the City Lancaster City
police officer police
brutality now I want to make something
clear I resigned from my position as
senior assistant public defender in
April of 2021 so what I am talking about
goes back
years
people and I would I'm also here in my
capacity as a Lancaster City resident I
pay taxes and this is my most recent tax
bill my property taxes are
41% of the city's
Revenue shame on that and the police
Bureau is
37% of the general fund
expense what
are the police doing with our money to
ensure Community safety
you know in the law there's a a
principle called proportionality but
people laymen non-lawyers we might call
it common sense how does it make sense
that armed men with a monopoly on
violence would be enforcing a Lancaster
count city ordinance that's punishable
by a maximum of $50 fine
make it makes
sense and exactly and this
ordinance indicates that lights and
reflectors be on
bicycles half an hour after Sunset all
the way through half an hour after
Sunrise the next day do you all know
sitting here when sun set on March
2nd I don't even think even on the
flimsiest
[Music]
flimsiest uh ground that the police have
nothing to stand on here they this is
straight up bullying and I do not
than I just
appreciate thank you I'm about to wrap
up thank you very much but as a taxpayer
I do not want my money to be spent on
these armed men bullying black and brown
children I have worked with black and
brown children over the last three years
I have worked with black and brown
children and they are [ __ ] gems okay
so I want to ask a couple things one
please please consider the proposed
resolution that has been introduced
tonight please please consider putting
officer Hatfield on desk Duty please
please acknowledge what has happened
because a failure to acknowledge what
has happened a repetition of the
[ __ ] uh excuse that the police put
out on W G earlier is only going to
serve to divide this community further
what we need is
accountability and it wouldn't hurt if
you paid for these children's therapy
time the sunet
right Mr Harris our next speaker please
next speaker is AIS
Martinez is Iris
here no our next speaker Mr
Harris jacn will will
good evening
[Music]
hello uh my name is jacqulyn Willman uh
I am a resident of the 100 block of East
Clay Street and I'm here tonight because
I'm a member of the cycling community
and I'd like to speak about the recent
events where the city has made the
streets unsafe for
everyone on March 2nd some young people
on bikes were stopped by the Lancaster
City police Bureau these boys did not
experience Safe Streets despite the
ongoing work by the city instead they
experienced quite the opposite when they
were harassed and assaulted by police
officers over not having front lights a
city police officer placed his knee on a
kid's back over this a city police
officer shoved and harassed a woman
passing by for filming their actions a
city police officer maed one of these
boys there have been some public
incidences of Lancaster City police har
harassing cyclist in the past all while
simultaneously breaking laws themselves
regarding safe
passing until
now nothing has escalated like the
incident on March 2nd and this incident
only escalated because these kids
weren't
white as has been mentioned earlier the
penalty for not having a front light
after Sunset is a fine of not more than
$50 there is no way to justify the
actions that occurred on March 2nd no
matter what happened before the video
started I am requesting that the city
terminate the employment of all of the
officers involved in this
incident these officers have proven that
given the opportunity they will harm
people and One Bad Apple spoils the
entire Barrel
I would also like to request that
following these officers terminations
the city reinstate a civilian review
board people who like to hurt people and
exert power over others are a poison to
our entire community and they need to be
removed from positions of
power thank
you Mr Harris if my notes are correct
that was our final pre-registered public
comment for this evening that's correct
thank you uh I will remind folks we do
have a second comment period at the end
of the meeting for issues that weren't
on the agenda which you're welcome to
stay for um we do have our uh
legislative agenda before us this
evening uh but if you are uh wishing to
uh leave at this time you can do so um
we will move on with the meeting and I
want to thank everyone for their
comments this
evening Mr will say something about this
today I'm so sorry on social media said
he was going to speak on this today so I
was kind of want to read we do I'm sorry
we do also have Council comments further
on in the agenda just when I plan to
make comment thank you yep good
point um so as as we will continue with
the agenda our next item is reports
requested by Council Mr Harris I'm
confirming that we don't have any of
those on the agenda this evening is that
correct we do not M thank you all right
we will then move to reports of
Committees of Council meetings which
were held on March 3rd 2025 our first is
Public Safety Council Diaz is not in the
room at the moment so we'll forgo her
report the next is Public Works
committee councelor her your report
thank you council president the Public
Works committee did meet on our
committee meeting excuse me March 3rd um
there was no legislative action taken or
considered um but we did hear a report
from the Department of Public Works on
the city's revamped uh trees for people
program um they gave us a lot of
exciting updates about things coming
this year uh including the planting of
376 Street trees um and uh you can learn
more um sorry at city of lster pa.gov
servic Tre and that concludes the Public
Works committee report thank you very
much councelor H Economic Development
Committee councelor men uh thank you
council president the economic
development committee did not meet in
our last session thank you Council Royo
finance committee thank you council
president uh the finance committee did
meet we discussed uh Administration bill
number 2025 uh which does appear later
in the agenda for its first reading that
concludes my report council president
thank you uh I will also turn to you for
Community planning committee in the
absence of council
Craig yes thank you uh Community
planning uh committee did meet during
the last session uh we discussed two
resolutions uh resolution number 19 2025
excuse me uh 20 2025 and resolution
number 22 2025 which also appears later
in the agenda uh that concludes my
report thank you turning to Public
Safety uh C back councilor Diaz uh yes
we had uh met um and we spoke on
resolution 18
2025 which would be um removing all the
um older records um and disposing them
and I will bring that up on on our next
agenda
legislation thank you uh and personel
committee councelor
pleas thank you madam president the
personal did meet on March 3rd and we
review nomination for appointment to the
city revitalization an improvement
district auor and a reappointment to the
Board of Health that concludes my report
Madam president thank you very much we
will now move into our legislative
agenda where the first item are
nominations for appointments councelor F
thank you Madame President those
nominations were reviewed on March 3rd
there isn't anything to add so I'll make
a motion to appoint Steven gush to the
city vitalization and Improvement zone
for term from December 31st 2024 to
December 31st 2029 and we appoint
Jessica Emy to the Board of Health for a
term from March 31st
2025 to March 31st
2030 second thank you we have a motion
and second on the appointments any
Council comments on
those comments from the public on the
appointments good evening good evening
um my comment is on the member the
people are rejecting Council um the
member that um the gentleman that came
in from another city to be on the board
of the revitalization board he does not
have experience nor did go to uh any
type of training in city of Lancaster to
know um like when we get graduates uh
and we go into act 101 or certain
different members um associations to be
on the board there's steps that need to
be followed with Lancaster City Alliance
and we feel that an outsider should not
hold that position so we reject the
gentleman that's coming in from another
city who clearly stated in our last
meeting that he has no experience
who's I speak on behalf of the people
maybe not you so and you're his wife so
understand comments to hear and everyone
and that's that's fine that's his wife
uh revitalization board that's your wife
that's
talking thank you Miss Gomez make a note
for folks in the room the Chris board uh
has several members a number of them are
City residents required um some of them
are open to other members uh in
Lancaster Community including business
owners and this particular uh gentleman
who came to our meeting on the 3 was an
appointee from Senator Scott Martin's
office which he has a seat uh on this
board to fill uh I believe he just has
the one seat on this board so we have
the majority of seats to fill this was a
a senator Martin appointment that was
brought before us on the third and who
is any additional comments from the
public on this
one on the appointments and who s that
Martin is to do
that Jose Rivera thank Andre Brock of
Coral
Street now who gave him the decision to
do
this th this is written into the bylaws
of the criis board so you guys are going
to hire from other cities to come here
here and tell us what to do or how to do
our neighborhood volunteer position this
is not a high but still we we we got
Alum knites from masi that could do that
that's right my grandson is in college
right now he could do
that and you go and get people from
outside to do
that wow thank
[Music]
you and I apologize it's not byw it's
state
law any additional comments from the
public on the appointments before
us County Das 700 block New Holland
Avenue uh just for the sake of education
and for future appointments um what are
the amount of positions and who can
appoint them for the Chris Authority
board how many are City exclusive how
might how many might be elected
officials and um I guess a follow-up
question to any of that is any
nominations made by elected officials or
other entities um is the city allowed to
request an alternative nomination be put
forward uh that's all I got thank you
thank you Mr dastra uh I don't believe
we are able to uh ask for an alternative
nomination unless there's more than one
that would come before us in this case
there was not there's nine members on
the Cris Bo and there are two non voting
members
which uh do uh represent Senator Scott
Martin's office by state law and also uh
City staff again they're non voting
members so the nine members again one is
an appointment from Senator maron's
office any additional comments from the
public on the
appointments darling bird uh and Street
I think this is an opportunity for
Council to help and educate the voters
and the public we come before council
with nominations for many of our
commissions and our authorities there's
very little information out there on
what the responsibilities what's the
requirement I feel there's a lack of
reaching out especially to the black and
brown Community to sit on these
authorities in these boards or to get
more local people Council needs to
figure a way out with our technology how
to educate the public about these so
when nominations are made and come up
here the information that we got today
should have been out there so we should
know so I'm just asking that Council
would take the time to educate people
about the commissions and authorities
how long they're serving why they're
serving 10 years why they're serving
five years and let us know thank
you espe ta any further comments from
the public on the appointments before
us council president Council as a member
of personel committee I do want to state
that Mr gr did come before the committee
at the Monday meeting uh Mr gr was
appointed U Mr gr was appointed by
Senator Scott Martin and he has been
practicing law in the city for many
years uh Scott Senator Scott Martin's
office believed that he would bring a
unique perspective and we did question
Mr G on how he uh plans to use criis to
uh promote Equitable economic
development in the city uh and we felt
comfortable with his answers as a
Personnel committee got to watch it
thank you
any additional comments on the
appointments hearing n Mr
Harris Mr I Mr Roy I Mr please I Mr
is I Mr h i pres b
i next item on the agenda are items for
the historic district Mr Harris if you
would when you're
ready considering the following
application and recommendation from the
historical Architectural Review Board
for improvements to a property within
the Heritage distri which within the
historic district uh we have one this
evening Stephen um Evangelista owner of
307 South Li Street request replacement
of a metal picture window on the facade
of a commercial building and that
application was Rec for approval by the
historical Architectural Review Board
thank you motion to approve second we
have a motion and a second uh councelor
Roy do you have any additional notes on
this one I thank you council president I
don't have anything additional um
Rebecca geyser is here this evening if
uh there's somewhere there's anything uh
you would like to add Miss
Geiser thank you just uh one additional
note that the harb found that the change
in the storefront window was an
appropriate modern alteration for the
use uh that was approved by the zoning
hearing board um and they unanimously
recommended this approval thank
you any additional Council comments on
the
recommendation from the
public hearing none Mr Harris Mr uh Mr
Royo hi Mr G hi m i Mr h i and president
b
i next item on the agenda these are
ordinance this is an ordinance for first
reading again there's no action being
taken on this one tonight it's
Administration bill number 2025 Mr
Harris an ordinance authorizing the
incurrence of non-electoral debt of the
city of Lancaster Lancaster County
Pennsylvania by the issuance of
principal amount of General obligation
bonds series of 2025 issued for the
purpose of providing funds for one
General Municipal projects including
upgrades and improvements City's
Wastewater collection and treatment
facilities the city's water treatment
and distribution facilities the city's
parks and related facilities the streets
and traffic signals within the city and
related facilities each is set forth on
exhibit a attached here here to and
other capital projects of the city as
determined by the city two capitalizing
interest on the bonds and three paying
the cost of issuing and ensuring the
bonds determining to sell the series of
2025 bonds the 2025 bonds at a private
Salway invitation approving the form of
the series of the 2025 bonds fixing the
number date interest and maturities in
the 2025 bonds making a covenant for the
payment of The Debt Service of the 2025
bonds pledging the full fake credit and
taxing power of this city in support of
such Bond bonds providing for the filing
of required documents providing for the
appointment of a sinking fund depository
for the 2025 bonds and authorizing
execution sale and delivery thereof and
other necessary action thank you Mr
Harris it's a lengthy title and I
appreciate that uh Council Roy do you
have anything to add at this time uh
nothing much to add just that the
expected uh total amount of the bonds is
is expected to be $ 38.4 million um for
projects that should be completed within
the next three years um that's all thank
you I'll make a note this was in my
notes from the um from the committee
meeting that the indebtedness was a part
of our 10-year projections that Council
was provided with over the course of the
last year plus um so this isn't new uh
planning this is just simply actually
taking out the bonds uh that were
projected to be done is that correct to
your
notes great any additional Council
comments again this is a first reading
tonight so there's no action being
taken from the
public johy dastra 700 block New Holland
Avenue uh I only have a question uh as
it relates to trash billing actually
because um you know I
think this gets a little weird and
complicated for me because utilities are
supposed to generate enough Revenue to
service themselves definitely recognize
that when your utilities need work you
got to finance the project somehow
otherwise you're drinking crap water uh
so I'm not knocking that but I would
like to know what the status is of the
most recent um I don't know if we've
requested the Pu change our rates for
out of city trash billing customers uh
so I just would like to know the status
of that since it kind of relates to
financing of these sort of projects
thank you Mr D it's my understanding we
don't have any customers trash outside
of the city any Sor yeah sewer okay
soorting to sewer and not trash yeah I
don't know why I was saying trash thank
you um water and sewer rate cases for
outside of the city I believe have
already started to be filed does anyone
have recollection of that in their notes
I don't have them in front of me but I
believe I recall that director Tina Camp
I didn't see you back there thank you um
yes so the the water rate has already
started the sewer rate will start once
the water rate is complete later this
year thank you for that
clarification any additional comments on
this one for first reading tonight again
no actions being taken this
evening good evening good evening Susie
Gomez
um this presentation that was done a
week week ago on this
Bond Lancaster City is paying for
contaminated
water that's number
one you got funding from 9 million to 7
million to fix pipes lead all this stuff
and you still want to attack the
homeowners and the
residents to change their lead
pipes what are you going to do
in terms of offering them some type of
solution rather than be like my father
where the city came in and said we need
to go in to replace these pipes we have
to see if you have lead pipes and then
told him oh yeah you need to replace
this and then my father said well how
much is it going to cost it was close to
$5,000 and when he came here to the city
and shared with the individual who's in
charge of this
that he wasn't able to pay they wanted
to condemn the property that he lives
in you guys need to be a little bit
more
accountable for everything and it's
unfair now the bond the guy uh mentioned
borrowing to save more tomorrow this is
a
long-term borrowing process that's going
to take 25 years of taxpayers money that
we're going to have to repay
I don't think Tina Campbell did a great
job in introducing this to the public
because many of us are still
confused okay we have the right to know
details and we have the right to hold
you accountable in any proceedings that
has in this city especially neighborhood
engagement s Miss go please address your
comments to council so I say that
because there is not enough information
that is being given to the taxpayers in
Lancaster City about decisions that you
guys are making that we have to follow
protocol on time I that I need everybody
in the room to please come to order we
will have decorum during the meeting
Miss gumes please continue your comments
this that's not go does not go against
your time the debt is $391 million and
I'm not saying that this occurred in the
last two years I'm saying that this
occurred in the last seven years the
water uh issue that we have in the plant
was known 30 years ago we are sitting on
our last 10 years as to whether or not
you guys raised enough money to change
that water system that is decades if not
centuries
old and we have to stand here and watch
increases in our utility bills but you
guys don't have no remedy it is shameful
okay there's a woman on Fremont Street
who took a shower and her skin was
literally peeling and you guys went in
and replaced her pipes and then sent her
a letter we have lead in our water we
know these things what is the
solution to tax us more money to make it
more harder for the average American
citizen for the taxpayers in Lancaster
City to provide food on their table for
their
children you guys don't have have no
Solutions you keep hiring Outsiders to
conduct business in our city that don't
know [ __ ] about
Lancaster thank
you I'll remind Council that the
detailed list of projects were included
with the bill and are posted and
publicly available they do include
infrastructure improvements for lead R
leadline replacement and Transit aging
pipe replacement so this is in part um
paying for the infrastructure that is
long overdue and has been long deferred
in the city of Lancaster any additional
comments on the first reading of this uh
bill again no council action will be
taken this
evening I just wanted to take a moment
to ask that again with your name sorry
my name is Taylor Raymond I live on the
500 block of St Joseph Street um I just
wanted to take a moment to ask the city
clerk to please speak up I was having
trouble hearing them thank you
noted any additional comments on the
ordinance for first
reading good evening hi my name is Lucas
I live in the 400 block of West Maran uh
just so the public has knowledge of
where to find this uh where could we
look at these ordinances before next
meeting great question uh all of our
proposed legislation and proposed res
Solutions are listed on the city website
under city council if you go to the top
across the top it says city government
you can click to council the bottom of
the page there are blocks where you can
click to see proposed resolutions
adopted resolutions proposed legislation
those are bills and adopted uh
legislation so bills that have been
adopted by Council they go back for many
many meetings and agendas for all
meetings once they're finalized are
available in the same place uh as well
as links to our YouTube page for
watching recordings of previous meetings
uh or watching them live so thank
you any additional comments on the bill
before us again for first reading no
actions to be taken
tonight hearing none we'll close that
we'll move on to our next item on our
agenda uh this is resolutions
resolutions we begin with uh resolution
number 18 2025 Mr Harris a resolution of
the Council of the city of Lancaster
authorizing the disposal of certain
obsolete records in Conformity with the
retention and disposition schedule for
records of Pennsylvania
municipalities council president if I
may Council council president as you
previously mentioned at the start of the
meeting I had made a requested report uh
for our next meeting of council uh from
the public safety um and uh although
this is a routine resolution I believe
it is best to table it until we have
that report at our next meeting so I
make a motion to table this resolution
until our next meeting Council after the
report
requested the resolution is not on the
table yet in order to to be Ted okay so
we need a motion to move it forward
before motion to table Yeah we need a uh
need a motion in a in a second in order
to bring it to I will make a motion to
bring It Forward second and we have a
second then councelor Amed uh is your
motion this evening to table until which
date until our next meeting of council
um and uh after we had the report that
was requested thank you
do we have a second to table second
thank you very much uh Mr Harris if you
would call the roll the vote to table
this uh item this
evening Mr M i Mr Roy I Mr please i m d
i Mr h i and president big I thank you
this is tabled until our next
meeting all right our next resolution
before us this evening is resolution
number 19 2025 if you would please Mr
Harris a resolution of the Council of
the city of Lancaster appointing special
councel for the city of
Lancaster motion to approve so we have a
motion and a second counselors we spoke
at this at the March 3rd meeting this is
to appoint special councel to assist us
during our negotiation process uh with
our collective bargaining agreement
through the next year um this is this
doesn't commit us to spend any money um
we heard a report from uh believe
director Tina Campbell on this um
stating that it is an hourly rate that
we would pay if we choose to or we do
engage the council uh but we must adopt
this resolution in order to use their
services there any additional Council
comments on the
resolution from the public
Mr D tiny dastra 700 Block in New
Holland Avenue um question of
clarification this collective bargaining
does it affect the collective bargaining
for the police
Union no it does not this is our apps me
against this apps me okay not the police
okay okay thank you any additional
comments from the public on the
reservation Miss gz now I just want to
make the public aware that uh the uh
fees would be
$365 an hour or some cost to that effect
for this Council or
attorney can you clarify that AB Mr
Harris do we have that in our notes from
the previous meeting I don't have my
notes in front of me it was something to
look into that it was in the minutes of
the previous meeting it was the minutes
thank you give me just a moment and I
would be happy to find for you yeah that
way we can inform the public on
things going
on end
[Music]
ofe $365 an hour would be the hour
hourly rate if we choose and we do use
the attorney during this year yeah from
taxpayer dollars because you can't do
your
job any additional Council uh excuse me
any additional com public on resolution
19 good
evening uh good evening um Nicholas
Rodriguez 100 block of East Walnut
Street um just for uh clarification
education um could you um describe some
use cases where it would be necessary
for either the city or the council to
call on this special Council
sure these are for labor negotiations
specifically um director Campbell if you
could provide a little bit of insight on
ways that we may have used special
Council for labor negotiations in the
past these aren't uh criminal or civil
court cases these are not courtroom um I
don't want to mischaracterize them as
mediation but perhaps you could provide
some insight on that yeah it's not
called mediation but it's uh similar to
that so they would um potentially help
with uh negotiations we if we get to a
point where we can't agree on certain
things within the contracts um those
would be negotiated through the attorney
um we they would also help us to make
sure that the contract language is clear
so there's no questions about that um
for the asme employees moving forward so
if we choose to engage them that would
be the point that we do correct thank
you any additional comments from the
public on the
resolution hello again uh just uh
regarding the previous comments
um so they wouldn't be paid or charged
until we engage with them in regards to
possible arbitrations correct okay
cool any additional comments from the
public on the
resolution Haring on Mr Harris Mr Med I
Mr Royo I Mr please
I I Mr I pres b i
our next resolution is resolution number
2025 Mr Harris if you would a resolution
of the Council of the city of Lancaster
approving the adoption of an amendment
to the ACT 537 official sewage
facilities plan for the city of
Lancaster Mo to approved second we have
a motion a second councilor Roy thank
you council president uh this resolution
is to um expand the sewage capacity this
specific plan amendment is for single
building containing four apartments and
it's going to be constructed when a
vacant
lot thank you very much Council Royo um
I also have in my notes in the previous
meeting that this is a property that's
outside of the city so it's sewer uh for
um nonresident uh account holders um and
I'll just might remind the public that
we do sewage facilities plan uh modules
every time there is any sort of
development and it's done to ensure that
we have sewage capacity so by passing
this it we have the city has found that
we have capacity for the project are
there any additional uh Council comments
on the
resolution from the
public hearing none Mr Harris Mr M i Mr
Roy I Mr pleas i m di I Mr h i president
Baker
I and we also have resolution 22 2025 Mr
Harris a resolution of the Council of
the city of Lancaster approving the
adoption of an amendment to the act by
37 official sewage facilities plan for
the city of Lancaster motion to approve
second have a motion and a second
councel Roy thank you council president
uh similar to the last resolution um
except this one is for the construction
of three new single family attached
homes on 617 Fremont Street thank you
very much any Council comments on the
resolution from the
public caring on Mr Harris Mr M i Mr
royya I Mr please i m i Mr h i president
v
i that concludes our legislative agenda
this evening we now move to our second
public comment period this is open for
items that were not previously on the
agenda duration of comments again is
three minutes per speaker and please
begin with your name and your block of
residence for our meeting record if You'
like to make public comment please
proceed to the podium at this time
good evening hi Jose Rivera uh 100 block
of uh Coral Street
um this
Saturday at Crystal Park the West
Crystal
volunteers will be helping and
supporting Janet Diaz and we'll be
giving out reflectors for the bikes for
kids if you guys want to come down and
join us we'll be at Crystal Park from
11:00 to
1:00 uh so we'll be doing that in our
neighborhood make sure the kids get
their reflectors because that was the
reason they will stop am I right right
and they and they brought like we would
all right so we will be giving our
reflectors thank you thank
you good evening hi uh cordel Booth uh
400 block of Locust Street um here to
talk
about uh my friends who got assaulted by
the police I know that there were a
bunch of comments made tonight but those
were by adults who don't know these kids
those three kids I know when I go to
school
with um when I I watched that my gosh I
watched that post five times that night
when I I saw it broke my heart
immediately I didn't know them like
actually but I've been working on
getting to know them and I've been
creating a better relationship with them
because of
this I'm a student representative on my
school board I plan to bring it up then
next Tuesday on our at our
meeting because and honestly
it's fine it's not okay because our
school district hasn't said a word about
it and those are our students that's not
okay I'm a member of the neighborhood
Leadership Academy at M high school I'm
going to bring it up tomorrow when we
have our meeting because other students
at my school need to know what is going
on in my community and our community
sorry I'm kind of trembling uh it's it's
uh it's kind of hard for me to talk
about without getting emotional because
this isn't okay and it's been going on
for hundreds of years and it's not okay
anymore and I'm not going to sit back
like I did in 2020 and just watch it
happen I'm going to stand up and I'm
going to use my voice and I'm going to
tell you guys
um but yeah I call for the firing of
Officer Hatfield and any of the other
officers that were just randomly unnamed
which is not okay also because they were
there too they could have stopped this
[ __ ] from happening but they did it
and that's also not
okay yeah I didn't write anything down
so thank
you proud of you your mom should be
really proud of you thank you for coming
here tonight additional comments from
the public
hello good evening my name is Patrice
Richards I live on a 300 block of um new
doorware um to piggy back off of the
students not knowing my husband is a
teacher in the district he did not know
about this until I told him I was going
to be coming here this evening he ran
into a former student of his who is now
going to masy who Cycles my husband is
also a cyclist and he said in this
interaction with the student um he was
harassed by a police officer telling him
he should not be riding his bike on the
street and that he actually should be on
the
pavement so I think it's really funny
that we're getting on the cases about
children not knowing about reflectors
lights etc etc and police officers don't
even know what they're enforcing and my
concern is that this child is now going
to be on the pavement and he's going to
run into an officer that says you're
supposed to be on the street and he's
going to relay no
I was told to be on the pavement and
then another incident like this can
occur so not only do the babies need to
know about the traffic laws we as the
adults need to know but also the people
who are enforcing the traffic laws
should know about that I literally he
literally told me this as I was walking
out the house and that's not okay I'm
like just like for us as Citizens
ignorance of the law isn't enough to be
ex exempt from it it goes for the people
who are actually doing the police
Leasing and the enforcing thank
you good evening good evening uh my name
is Jenny calibri I live on the 500 block
of North Street and I'm nervous to
public speak and I think it always helps
to call that out um I believe that
knowledge is power and so I want to
share some context on the history of the
police state um the first sort of like
official unofficial Place state that we
saw in America was in the 1700s in the
Carolinas um they were called slave
patrols slavery was Central to the
economy and so these slave patrols were
one of the most egregious treatments of
mankind in human history um they were
especially cruel in the ways that they
captured runaway slaves and punished
them for daring escape and this was the
start of placing in
America after slave liy was abolished
During the Reconstruction Era um cruelty
was the policing style and polies were
used as a way to provide a sense of
security for white communities and they
aim to keep black communities
intimidated and segregated from the
white
population knowledge is power um the
police state started as a way to control
black and brown people in this country
that has not changed that does not
change if we cannot recognize that that
is the truth of American history and the
police state in this
country black and brown people have
historically been brutalized at the
hands of people in power starting in the
1700s alone just in a police state not
even acknowledging the slave trade that
started before that um they have
historically been brutalized at the
hands of people in power and they are
equally neglected the benefit of the
doubt which is always afforded to white
people
always we need to call this what it is
it is a clear abuse of power we've seen
play out over hundreds and hundreds of
years of
History um next I want to say that every
single person sitting in this room every
person is in this room because they were
a kid and they survived being a kid
black and brown kids are also kids those
kids riding their bikes are also kids
and they deserve to be kids and they
deserve to grow up they deserve to grow
up in this city in this community with
their neighbors and friends and people
who care about them and look out for
them and protect them and who signed an
oath and took a position of power to
protect them and then continued to
neglect to do that there's not a single
human being in this city on this Earth
who deserves to take that right away
from them and this was absolutely
wrong and unacceptable thank
you good evening good evening uh my name
is Taylor enterline I live in the
Manheim burrow I work in the city and
have basically grown up in the city um
I'm also one of the organizers part of
the collective statement that we have
put out
um so many thoughts um and I want to
point out the ab absence of the mayor um
because our demands really need to be
said to her and all of y'all that a
civilian review board is needed I know
that there was this police working group
supposed has transitioned in 2024 and
since the 3 months we have been in 2025
we have seen the escalation of police
violence that has been recorded that has
been recorded from the violence on black
and brown people and black and brown
children in our community and also this
happened on March 2nd all of us saw the
videos on the on that uh following
Friday and then all these statements
have came out and I won't reiterate what
people have said but but the statement
from the police is
unacceptable I am
wondering I wondering specifically for
council member aroyo and Diaz as future
mayor of the city what are your plans to
implement to ensure trust in our
community for the police to promote
Public Safety to work with the
organizations that are reaching out to
try and better like these commitments
and so I will just leave it at that and
to really sit with like the student who
just spoke and who the black and brown
children who are who are experienced
this as a person who also went through
the police violence of this city from
2020 and now we're about to put kids
through the system because of the
charges they're putting out that again
should just be a fine and had to go
through that trauma is
unacceptable it's trauma and it's and
it's reiteration of that power that they
are trying to put on on the black and
brown people and the children and it's
not okay and it's unacceptable thank
you darling bird and Street I just want
to make some clarity we're talking about
having a a review board the city of
Lancaster has never had an independent
police review board or Community review
board we keep talking about reinstating
it there was not one the review board
needs to have some teeth to it a lot of
this was bought up when we used to have
Public
Safety when we used to have Public
Safety meetings and Council would have a
day that they met and you would get to
come in and discuss public safety issues
and the other different departments so
maybe before a lot of your time but this
was addressed then and I just want to
make that clear when we're asking for a
a review board we're asking for
something that has teeth not what we've
had
but something new and we're asking
Council to act on it now we don't want
to wait till we get a new mayor we don't
want to wait till we get for new
councilmen this is something or Council
women this is something that we can do
right now and I think you have heard
from the public and we're asking Council
to take action on this and go ahead and
let's have this independent review board
thank you than you
pastor Kevin Brown of Kingdom Life
International assembly 900 East King
Street I did not come prepared to speak
tonight but it is obvious that there's
tension in the community about this
incident and about the ongoing issues
with the police department and the
public it has
reached um a situation where now the
youth are at risk because there is not a
proper
relationship between law enforcement and
the
community my question
is um since we have already and I know
that I've been a part of um
conversations about having a a community
uh review
board years ago and um there was no real
um attention given to it I am saddened
that the mayor and the chief of police
is not here
tonight because the mayor and the chief
of police should be answering to the um
behaviors of the officers that committed
these atrocities with the
community and and I'm I would like to
suggest that after a proper
investigation is
initiated and officer Hatfield and the
others are removed from their
position so that there is no further um
controversy in that regard about whether
a police officer who has already
committed an atrocity
towards the community is still allowed
to um execute
policing that the
public um Safety
Committee would possibly do a town hall
meeting and with the mayor and the
police chief being there to hear from
the
community what should be needed to
rectify by this situation as well as
ongoing uh efforts to um try to bring
some healing to this situation with the
disparities between the police or law
enforcement and the community thank you
thank
you good evening good evening thanks so
much for hearing our comments tonight uh
my name is Samantha swager I'm on the
100 block of northan Street um I had not
seen the police's response to the police
response until this evening when I
looked it up and I just wanted to call
attention to um something that caught my
eye it reads the individuals involved in
the incident have had several
interactions with the police Bureau for
trespassing and garages pulling fire
alarms blocking travel Lanes riding near
pedestrians and causing traffic issues
putting others and themselves at Danger
in danger um and I just want to point
out that that sounds like any given day
at the high school middle school boys
and girls club the mix in the hallways
like these are kids um they they sound
like they're being kids it sounds like a
prefrontal cortex that isn't fully
formed and won't be for another 10 years
if we're talking about the individuals
that were involved in the March 2nd
incident um and I bring this recent
police incident of brutality up and I
bring this up because I have a
background in working with youth I have
friends who work with youth I have
friends who are teachers and staff at
schools many of whom make far less than
our police force
do um and they would never be allowed to
treat a child in this way kids get
annoying they do silly things and then
they get sent into detention and we we
do some repair work that's not what
happened
here if if a professional that works
with youth ever acted in this way with a
youth they would be barred for work from
working with youth moving
forward and it would follow them it
would follow them throughout their
entire professional career thereafter so
if we're looking at our teachers and Our
Youth Development professionals and we
demand that level of accountability with
folks who work with youth on a daily
basis and deal with these kinds of
incidents every day then I think we need
to hold the same level of accountability
for the folks that our taxpaying dollars
go towards thank
you hello Matt Hoyer I live on the 600
block of West Chestnut um before I begin
I would like to Echo the sentiments that
have been expressed tonight um but I'm
here today to ask that the city
reexamine The Pedestrian safety of the
intersection of College Avenue Pearl
Street and Columbus Columbia
Avenue current situation the
intersections focused around Columbia
with pearl and college being offsets the
traffic signals are in order Colombia
Pearl college and The Pedestrian
Crossings illuminate with the green
light um this is normal for many
intersections but I believe that this is
a bad idea for this particular one this
is because drivers making left turn s
out of Pearl and college tend to charge
through the intersection without paying
attention to the crosswalks and unless
someone's already in the middle of the
street then they may not get a chance to
cross until all the red light Runners
have gone through and if you don't think
there's red light Runners then you have
not been a
pedestrian
um this is something that I have both
seen and experienced many times
personally including for example last
Friday around two 2:30 p.m. where I
watched a jogger not able to cross the
intersection after until all 20 cars had
gone
through I believe that fixing this issue
is especially important because of two
nearby bus stops at Columbia and Pearl
and Colombia and Ruby which serve the
Millersville and Columbia bus routes in
fact this is the main reason why I
personally tend to cross Columbia at
this
point I understand that there's only so
much that the city can do due to the
wonky nature of the built environment
however I'd still like to see the city
do something in regards to pedestrian
safety to make pedestrians feel safer
Crossing this intersection in accordance
with its own Safe Streets
plan my suggestion is to light the
pedestrian signals at College at Pearl
and college a few seconds before the
green light much like the city does with
its downtown area in order to give
pedestrians a chance to get into the
intersection so that the drivers can
actually see them and then maybe
hesitate frankly I'm I don't know the
actual numbers but frankly I'm I'd be
surprised that more people haven't been
hit injured killed at this intersection
thank you for your time thank
you evening H good evening uh Nicholas
Rodriguez uh 100 block of East W net
um I've lived in Lancaster since I was
about three I went to
masi uh I don't have experience working
with children but I've experience as a
child
um a few years ago
uh
I I'm pu ran as you can see visibly
Brown uh and growing up I was always
told uh don't call the police on someone
you're not willing to see
that
and uh for good reason because once you
make that call that power is out of your
hands and uh I've seen a lot of
situations where it would be helpful to
have a third party
um
to you know at least separate um the
people involved you know in instances of
um domestic violence things uh of that
nature
but when there's that potenti when
there's that potential of this do I want
to see this person permanently punished
do I want to see this person's life
ruined or do I just need them to stop
what they're doing now when you're given
that choice a lot of people are going to
understandably
choose not to engage the
police which then makes them feel less
unsafe because the other you know your
only other option is try to argue with
this person or a nuclear weapon you're
going to you know try to stick it out
even though you will continue to be in
danger um and people a lot of people
said um
I think it's honestly
unfair for the uh chief of police and
the mayor to not be here to saddle all
our public comment with you all you know
you've um an important job but it's
limited in scope the specific things you
can do aren't as you know the mayor and
the chief can change things
immediately there's only so much you all
can do um
so uh uh thank you for hearing us all
out thank you
Tony asra 700 block New Holland Avenue
before I forget I want to actually agree
with uh Mr Matt Boyer back there that
there should be a study done at that
intersection and if a study is done I'd
encourage you to look into evaluating
Allway stops or Allway Crossings where
everything's a pedestrian uh Crossing
all at once uh I think they're great but
I digress because that's not why we're
here tonight or at least not why I came
tonight um I agree with the members of
the public that are uh upset that that
the mayor is not here tonight as well as
the chief of police um ultimately like I
don't want to give too much Flack here
but like ultimately the mayor is the
conductor of the concert that is police
and chief of police is first violin you
guys are like the Rhythm Section like
you're important you have the ability to
push this concert forward or bring it
back um but that being said it is a
concert and this issue of policing
should become increasingly important for
our local communities is we are
concerned with Federal
destabilization you know ultimately a
people needs to be in concert with its
people who have Force because we are
living in an era where we don't know
who's necessarily fighting for our
rights anymore we want to know that our
police are doing that
um you know I I understand where
everybody's coming with we need to fire
uh officer Hatfield I believe it is but
we also have the problem of there's a
police Union there are procedures for
terminating officers and those sometimes
Wow Come In conflict with what we're
looking to see as a community at a
certain point in time so the investig
invest investigations need to continue
but it doesn't remove the fact that
right now there's clearly a disconnect
between the public and policing and I
also agree with the public that we
really need to establish the citizen
review board in the 21st century we
don't get the opportunity to do these
internal investigations where the
evidence is in the police headquarters
and it's reviewed or taken to a third
party we are living in an era where
everyone is an investigator everyone's a
reporter everyone has a camera so we
really should aim to have a more
cohesive process for how we can work
through these issues because ultimately
we need a good police force we need to
know who's on our side
this is a complicated matter but we've
we have unfortunately been through this
use of force concern before we need to
break this cycle thank you thank
you hello Lucas again from 400 West
Maran um based on all these comments uh
today I believe we are all under the
impression that in a way we are under
Fire from the
police um that being said there is a
disturbing Trend within this country of
the gradual and continual militarization
of
police we cannot be expected to be
protected by a force who treats us as a
threat and as
prey and that is how a lot of these um
people are being trained either they're
having Retreats and going on these
specific uh being taught by tutors who
teach these uh officers to treat us as
constant
threats when we do have a citizen review
board not if when we have a citizen
review board I believe it's a necessity
that we also take a good look at how we
are training our officers and if these
individuals are coming from the military
that they are receiving the um proper
therapy and Trauma uh care that they
need to come back from an active combat
zone into civilian life
thank you thank
you good
evening hi okay good I don't really talk
in my microphones all day so I'm going
to try and make this as streamlined as
possible if you could just begin with
your name and block of residence yep my
name is roow Potter I'm on the 600 block
of South Franklin Street I wasn't really
sure how that worked until I got up here
I come here tonight not fully educated
on what was going on with the car uh the
cops sto that uh the two young
individuals earlier in the week and it
took my partner bringing it to my
attention for me to get a reaction out
of it and this is important to me
because I'm sweaty stinky and smelly
from spending all day educating and
working with kids for the
YWCA I sit thank you I see a few of my
YW friends around here somewhere I can't
pinpoint you but I see you I spend all
day working with these kids and telling
them them to look up to the people that
are making our laws and running our
country and I got to tell them the
president of the United States or a
government official isn't exactly what's
going to change the footing of our
society and in fact I think everyone
should look around at who's actually
here tonight and who left Midway to give
their comments in the beginning this is
actually who's listening who's affected
and who is going to make the change they
can listen but it's like my friend said
four they are the people stopping the
main comments from getting to the top so
what we say actually matters but what we
do and what we rally is actually way
more important than me getting up here
and saying this on a microphone so
please everyone look at each other get a
name get a phone number get a Instagram
or whatever talk
organize we don't have to put up with
this we really don't we really don't
Jessica Lopez Lancaster resident I
promise I'm not coming back to yell
jues
um one let me say that yes there are
unions and you
still without Union issues put that man
on the desk don't let him out his office
you don't want to fire him he's hiding
behind the
union put him in the office
do not give him a gun do not allow him
to run around our
city no Union can stop you from doing
that and yes I get it y'all are not the
key element in this movement but you are
here to uphold the one person who is
supposed to uphold the chief
yeah so yes this is on use y and I get
it some of y'all like
her y'all are not here to protect her
feelings you are here to protect us
that's
right and then in that protection I ask
what does the safety working committee
do is it to prevent and protect and
bring safety measures before for the
issue or is it to allow an issue to bust
out and then be like Oh Come to Crystal
Park we'll give you free reflectors
you're too late
Janet it was your job as the Safety
Committee to have this education put out
before those panhandling notices came
out because y'all managed to do that
real
quickly I'm disgusted Beyond disgusted
we're not tired of the white
representative we're not tired of the
black representative we're tired of the
complacent representative that thinks
they're going to come in here Lean Back
be
comfortable and capitalize off of us
that's what we're tired of Janet so you
could quote me on
that and to the guy that just came up
here I want you to know
that those people that left they work
tirelessly day in and day out to clean
this city up not every one of them but
understand that we don't get paid for
all our hours heck I just started
working for the bail fund I've been
doing this I've been coming to see y'all
for how many years
now I just started getting paid for
this yay
and yes I reiterate that it is up to the
city to educate these children and it is
up now to our community to give them
those reflectors we don't need our kids
around you gaslighting like
[Music]
that good evening good evening um Diane
Desmond I live off root 30 Stones throw
away from the state police um so I
wanted to um in the interest of keeping
the council accountable there was a
promise during the first round of uh
public comments that you would recall
the names of the people who were not uh
first there and I just was hoping that
you could do that yeah typically do that
at the very end I see folks behind you
and I am planning to do so so thank
you good evening good evening my name is
SOA Rosa um former Lancaster City
resident now I live in Lancaster
Township
and I also
yes so beta Rosa formerly Lancaster City
resident current Lancaster Township
resident also uh co-founder of the
Lancaster change makers
Collective I've heard a lot of people
talk about that there's not a proper
relationship between the police and the
community but there is a
presence there is a presence in the
schools the school district pays these
four school resource officers what are
they doing if not educating the students
on how they can ride bicycles in their
own community that is very confusing to
me
also the police do their rounds at least
in the Southeast When I visit my
grandparents When I visit my friends
they are doing their rounds their
presence is known those SUVs you can see
them coming but they are not talking to
the people that live in those
communities
that is crazy to
me also the police made this statement
on March 10th this incident happened on
March 2nd so without public outrage were
they not going to address it was nothing
going to happen was no investigation
going to happen are we just allowed to
brutalize people and they had the body
camera footage who's analyzing that
somebody saw that footage other officers
saw Hatfield knee somebody is there no
accountability Within in that
organization and they have a union to
protect them to keep brutalizing people
that's
insane for my job that I get paid for I
go into the Youth Intervention Center
three times a month to talk about
healthy relationships with the youth
three times a month I see children in
Orange sweaters in Gray sweatpants with
no shoes on in a room for an hour they
get padded before they come in they get
padded down before they leave they are
up for 12 hours a day and when they're
not in classes or in programming they're
in a Cell these are children that are
incarcerated they have to earn extra
privileges like nice soap and an extra
phone call so if these if we don't drop
the charges if you're not behind
dropping the charges for this for these
youth they will become incarcerated they
will be become part of a dehumanizing
system and then what does that say are
we just saying that they're not worth
anything because they're black and brown
and because they dare to ride a bike
outside in their own
Community y that's all I have to
say typically we we have one uh free
minutes but it's your first meeting and
I appreciate you being here
so all right honestly I wanted uh
Cordell Booth 400 block Lucas I just
said
whatever said um what that lady said
before me I forgot her name I'm sorry uh
she's right what the hell are the school
resource officers doing at my
school I listen I respect them I talk to
them I try to communicate with them I
mean for when I see them they don't do
anything they sit in the hallways and
they watch and wait for probably
students again to a fight that's not
okay and I want them to start teaching
students that are
uneducated about what they can about
laws because it's not okay and I want my
friends to be safe in my community
uh my friends invited me to play
basketball tonight at the park and I
told them no because I wanted to be here
because this was a little bit more
important than playing basketball but
also
because I remember being in middle
school and I was at that Park and there
were two of my of two other people on
the other side of the Court getting
absolutely harassed by officers asking
them questions and harassing them and I
didn't say a word because I was scared
I'm not scared
anymore I mean Miss Bay you heard you
said it I'm trying to make my mom proud
right now and every single day that I go
out and I represent her and my dad I
want to make I want to make them proud
man and every day that I see kids that
are going through this absolute BS I
can't take it anymore and I'm not just
going to like stand by and let it happen
and I'm going and I really do want the
mayor to be here and I want the chief of
police to be here cuz they need to hear
me and all of these other people talk
about what they should do because again
as I've repeatedly had to say it's not
okay it's not when I leave next year
when I go off to
college whichever one of you two is the
mayor whichever one which I will be
voting in CU I'll be
[Applause]
18 But whichever one of you is the mayor
how are you going to protect my friends
that are still at masy that are still in
the middle schools that are still at
these programs that I summer camp
counsil at for months trying to teach
kids about the stuff that's happening in
this messed up world and how they can
stay safe and be and still be together
and have community and feel Community
this all these people I don't know any
of these people except for a few I've
never honest I don't know if I'm ever
going to see them again right everybody
here is
different everybody here is a different
color different shade different hair
we all deserve the same
respect and the last thing I'm going to
say about the police is
that thank God I'm not in that that I
was never in that
situation however I know I have a permit
I have a driving permit when I'm driving
on the roads whenever I see police not
only now so sorry Mom not only is my mom
scared sometimes when we drive past the
lease I have severe anxiety that's
diagnosed by a doctor I have anxiety
when I drive by by the police I can't I
shouldn't be scared they're there to
protect me I live in this city my
parents pay their my parents pay their
salaries I deserve to be safe in this
city along with everybody
else all right that's all I got
I want to give an opportunity as
mentioned before for the folks that
might have been on the list for the
first public comment period so I'm going
to say names I may butcher them but if
any of these folks are here please you
can come forward at this time uh Aaliyah
Moos Grace
muser um Megan
Keller uh Monda rits and an
Torres and Iris Martinez I believe were
the folks that were not here if I have
my notes correct so if any of them are
here please come forward um you not one
of those people that's fine I don't see
any of them right now they can walk
forward at this time but please go ahead
thank you thank you Council um I'm sorry
I'm an Tores you did okay thank you very
much I just my notes were a little
jumbled from earlier thank you good
evening thank you hi good evening Evelyn
Morales 900 block of wallbank Street um
I did not come here prepared to speak
tonight and just so you're aware who's
in the room um we have a group of Social
Work students here from Millersville and
so we are here to see um how our
government is functioning at a local
level and your response to community
concerns so please be aware that this is
the future you're sending
out
um that being said I'm a city resident I
have four kids in the district
and I just want to reiterate that yes
you know we should be teaching our kids
how to ride a bike but it's so much
information think about how long it took
you to try to to pass a permit a permit
to get your driver's license that is a
lot that you're asking a 10-year-old to
retain and on top of that we're changing
the streets to accommodate these bike
lanes and not no two streets are the
same so you're asking them to to learn
all this in real time when adults
can't so please when as you're
continuing to expand these bike Lanes
take that into consideration take into
consideration your audience have more
education in the schools and Reach
people where they are we talk about
different ways to reach people like
we're going to have a zoom meeting we're
going to have something in person we're
going to have something that's
walkable so please keep that in in mind
thank you thank you
any additional comments for this
period okay this is just for Susie Gomez
100 block of North Reservoir Street this
is just for clarity I am about to be 50
years old in 9 months I have a 32 year
old and a 27y old I literally had to
take to address an officer to remove the
handcuffs off of my son because he
pulled out of the back seat of a vehicle
okay and he immed well he just put them
on the floor as if they are just
dogs okay it is
disgusting I've been in this city since
1992 my daughter graduated from
Lancaster metanite she's 32 and my son
graduated from masy he's 27 I am not a
spring
chick okay I I was under the
administration with Ray di agustino who
is County Commissioner who was my boss
and I had dealings with a lot of people
in the
city I've done my due diligence I've
done my community work and I've damn
sure done my
homework okay and what I see is
unexplainable it's beyond words that's
why a lot of times I stutter because
it's
unbelievable how much red tape and how
much you're getting away
with there are people that need
housing there are issues in our city
that need to be
attended and it is not a rocket science
because 1 plus 1 equals two to handle
your responsibilities and address your
oath that you declared to serve the
people not the
administration it is shameful to not see
the mayor here or the police officer but
it's even more shameful how I can
actually witness being an exh Housing
Development coordinator how much damage
this Administration and other people in
power has done not only to our
neighborhoods I can't even drive in the
Southeast because I got to keep dodging
hoes because you guys don't even want to
pave the streets with taxpayer dollar
but you got all these infrastructures
you got all these plans for Lancaster
City and none of them can actually I
can't even tell my five grandbabies that
they have a future here because they
might not even afford to rent let alone
how to buy a
house it is shameful especially For You
motherless people that don't have a
child and are making decisions based on
taxpayer dollar you should be ashamed of
yourself ex you should do your job and
go out into the streets and actually get
to know the community meet with people
people that are paying your tax that are
paying your
salary there any further comments for
the second
period hi um Taylor Raymond again 500
block of St Joseph Street um are uh is
it normal for the mayor uh and the chief
of police uh to be at these meetings uh
is this an unusual circumstance that
they aren't here uh the chief of police
normally doesn't attend regular meetings
unless there's a report that's been
requested like we were talking about
earlier the mayor typically does attend
these meetings she has a prior
commitment um and was not able to be
here and that's as much as I can say I
don't have a way to compel the mayor um
to attend but typically yes okay thank
you
hi sorry I didn't have oh Leah strickler
um and I'm on North Charlotte Street um
I didn't have anything prepared today
but I wanted to speak on um the comments
that people made about education and
educating these kids and resources and
that sort of thing that's great but at
the end of the day what should be
happening is we should be holding these
police officers accountable it doesn't
matter if these kids don't know thew
laws they they aren't in school for
learning bike laws they're in
school they're these these police
officers are the ones that need to be
held accountable not these kids not
their parents not the community it's the
police brutality that's the issue thank
you thank
you charges Alesandra me block South and
Street up just have a quick question is
anybody filing assault charges against
these
officers
rep there any additional comments for
this period wait did she answer the
question did you answer the question
answer the question I have no knowledge
of any charges that are brought I I
don't know one way or the other has he
even been put on administrative lead I
do not know the answer to that question
do we get the answers I suspect that
there will be additional Communications
coming out from the police Bureau in the
coming days it's just on information
that I have at this time thank you I
personally went down and filed a
complaint with police officers I put it
on
Facebook so if you want action you down
and follow complain against thank you
good thank you are there any additional
public comments for this period she's
right Miss Rosa you you have already
gone so I'll give you just a moment if
you have additional comments thank you
it was just a quick question what's the
best way to reach out to counselors to
give our Grievances and to work with
y'all to get to see what we the change
that we want done obviously people can
just come and yell at you but like
what's the most productive way to get
stuff
done you're welcome to do that but um
each of us have a contact information on
the same City website that I was
referencing earlier about finding legis
I'm not sure if you're here for that
part um under the city of Lancaster it's
also just our first initial and last
name at city of lanter
dog and do you know have any information
about the social workers that work
within the police department and if they
were involved in this incident I have no
information about whether they were part
of this incident or not I have nothing
I've seen nothing to indicate that they
were but I don't know for sure thank
you are there additional comments for
this period
heing none go close the public comment
period this evening and I want to thank
everyone for your
participation um the next item on the
agenda would have been a report of Mayor
but I don't have one for par at this
time the next item is a report of
President of council um I did give a
statement earlier this evening so I
won't reiterate that but I will say um
that as a childless person um I am also
a city resident I work with children
every day as a director of program for a
nonprofit in a city that serves Youth
and I take deep offense but I'm not
qualified to make good
decisions for our residents simply
because I've chosen not to have a child
and that's nobody's
business but iuse to share that child
cannot afford her bre M Gomez thank you
you've given your comment tonight and I
take offense of that statement I would
just like to say that I like to believe
that I make good decisions and if you
don't believe that I make good decisions
please don't say that I do so because I
don't have child that's right thank
you we now open it up to comments from
Council comments from
Council
got um cuz I do want to address the the
the very full room that we have here
tonight um and I want to say thank you
all for coming um exercising your First
Amendment right to petition to assemble
and to protest and it's your right to
yell at us and we have to listen so
that's that's part of the job I really
don't have a lot to say I don't want to
say all that much about the incident
because all I'm going to say is that
there needs to be a thorough a thorough
investigation of the events because I
was disturbed by what I saw as a citizen
and as a
stepdad and I was an auditor so I looked
at details um when I was in that role I
looked at
documentation it has to be thorough
there cannot be holes um I don't see how
we get there without the body uh camera
footage coming out
personally we have a lot of uh a lot of
um between this resolution and I've
taken detailed notes on all the comments
that came here tonight we have a lot to
consider um when we legislate there are
details there there there are you know
state laws there are federal laws that
govern and and limit Us in some capacity
but all of these ideas uh I plan to
research them I plan to pursue them to
the extent that we can um alongside my
colleagues so again I'm not going to say
anything more um but I think Council has
work to do and the resource absolutely
has work to do in engaging the community
and earning their trust back yes
right additional comments from Council
council president for me I'm gonna go
right down the row if that's okay
abolutely Council Diaz I would like to
say that it was very disturbing watching
the
video and just like Amanda says just
because I don't have children it doesn't
mean I don't understand understand I
lost I lost a nephew who I was going to
adopt at the age of 17 because he had
cancer and he was bullied because he was
half white so I also understand that I
have worked with the police I have
worked very hard to find ways to make it
better but there is also the executive
which is the mayor that also has to make
decisions on any policy that's going to
come out yeah and it also goes through a
solicitor it's not something that is
very easily done but I just want to say
thank you for coming because it does
show that you do
care that's all I
have councelor uh thank you council
president um and I just wanted to thank
everybody who came out and spoke tonight
um and I was disturbed by the videos as
well um and you know some of the
comments that have been made today um uh
I resonated with about you know what is
the power of Council in these matters
and one of the powers of council is
reports requested for councel and that
is why I have requested a report um on
what the use of uh Force policy is uh
and what the review process will look
like and I look forward to seeing that
report uh and just one last comment um
you know we appreciate everybody who
comes out and uses their political
advocacy to speak at these meetings um
but I just want to um you know I I'm
very disturbed by comments especially
during women's History Month you know
calling out of elected officials for not
having children I mean we have to have
theorum in these Chambers I understand
people are uh very passionate about
these issues uh but you know we have
people who are working very hard and
whether we have children or not I mean
it's just unacceptable to be talking
about that um and I hope that we could
all learn from that and you know treat
each other with respect when you know
these are very uh distinguished Chambers
and I take this very seriously so these
comments about people being childless
especially in a month that we're
celebrating women's history is
unacceptable any additional Council
comments councilor R thank you council
president uh just wanted to address the
crowd that's here this evening um first
thank you for coming this evening to
share your thoughts your concerns your
ideas um you know as my colleagues have
mentioned you know part of the process
whenever we're trying to find Solutions
is coming together uh and even if the
conversations are uncomfortable they're
very very much important and uh it's
very um humbling to see the community
come together to to to drive some of
these Solutions I I saw the video um it
was brought to my attention by a friend
of mine that um I was not aware of it
before um and first I saw you know I saw
that video as myself God knows that I've
done worst things on my bike as a as a
teenager um and then I saw it as a
father uh my were you know we set a goal
for my son to learn how to ride his bike
this summer um so
first and foremost before being elected
official counselor whatever um that's
the lens that I'm seeing that video
through and um I expect any City
employee to have compassion uh empathy
and accountability for our residents and
you can do all of those at the same time
in a respectful compassionate Manner and
I I believe and I'm optimistic in the
leadership in this city including my
Council colleagues to come up with a
solution that will uh that will create a
culture where um as Mr Bo said uh make
everyone feel safe and that is the
priority of everyone that works for the
city of Lancaster um so thank you all
for coming tonight and uh we hear
you thank you
counc councelor C thank you Madame
President and thank you all for coming
and I already addressed the video on my
platform but I I understand the concern
raised by the community regarding the
video it was disturbing and it cause the
pain and
concerns every resident of Lancaster
deserve to feel safe and respected and
it it is important that all interactions
between law enforcement and City
residents are handled with
professionalism and respect I believe
that the department should conduct an
independent investigation and take
appropriate actions because moments like
this we cannot
AFF for to L this um unchecked thank you
all for
coming question I'm sorry sir yes since
everyone of the council
members has already
affirmed that you've seen the
video and it's disturbing to all of
you can you not the pressure on the
mayor to make some kind of decision yes
make sure this officer is at least put
on
administrative within the next 40 24 to
hours don't have additional comments
from the public this period but I
appreciate your question um the answer
is that yes uh I know that I will
personally be in contact with the mayor
tomorrow uh very first thing in the
morning on a calendar um and I believe
that the comments from members of
council affirm our commitment to making
sure that there's a resolution to this
um and that it is exped expeditious uh
whatever that resolution may be so thank
you uh we the end of our agenda for this
evening so uh at this time I'll hear a
motion to
adjourn motion to adjourn second a
motion and a second all in
favor we Jour thank
you it's so crazy see you